Guide to the Board of Research Associates in American Economic History Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Board of Research Associates in American Economic History papers
1902-1933
MS 88
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11
(22 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, reports, studies, minutes of meetings, circular letters, financial reports, outlines of proposed surveys, annual reports, departmental reports, and monographs relative to the established purpose of the Board, which was sponsored by the Carnegie Institution of Washington, Department of Economics and Sociology. Included are interviews (ca. 1906-1907) with Southern farmers, professionals, government officials, and merchants on the economics of agriculture in the South. Also a number of interviews with blacks connected with the Tuskegee Institute, an insurance agent, a banker and laborers. Topics covered in the collection include labor legislation in Indiana, 1908; laws regarding seamen; immigration; labor problems in individual states; public poor relief in Wisconsin; trade unions; school systems; child labor laws; and mining laws.
Board of Research Associates in American Economic History
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Board of Research Associates in American Economic History, 1934.
Arrangement
Arranged in three parts: corrrespondence, monographs, and account book.
Scope and Contents
The correspondence in this collection, arranged by the secretary of the Board of Research Associates, consists of 16 boxes. The entire collection consists of 23 boxes. These papers were arranged by Miss Vera Timm, Secretary of the Board of Research Associates, and were turned over to Yale Library. The Board in 1934 had voted to give the papers to Yale Library.
African Americans -- Economic conditions; Child labor -- New Jersey; Economics; Labor laws and legislation -- Indiana; Labor laws and legislation -- Iowa; Labor laws and legislation -- Kansas; Labor laws and legislation -- Maryland; Labor laws and legislation -- Michigan; Poor laws -- Minnesota; Poor laws -- Wisconsin; Public lands -- United States; Sailors; Social legislation -- United States; Labor unions -- United States; Southern States -- Economic conditions; United States -- Economic conditions; Historians; Farnam, Henry W. (Henry Walcott), 1853-1933; Board of Research Associates in American Economic History; Carnegie Institute of Washington
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - 1904 (Box 1)
    - 1902 May-1906 June (Box 1–2)
    - 1906 July-1908 March (Box 2)
    - 1908 April-1909 March (Box 3)
      General
      A-M
    - 1908 April-1909 March (Box 3)
      M-Z
    - 1909 April-1910 January (Box 3–4)
    - 1910 February-1911 January (Box 4)
    - 1911 February-1912 November (Box 5)
    - 1912 November-1914 September 20 (Box 5–6)
    - 1914 September 20-1915 June (Box 6)
    - 1915 July-1916 September (Box 7)
    - 1916 October-1918 January (Box 7–8)
    - 1918 February-1926 December (Box 8)
    - 1927 January-1934 (Box 8–9)
      Material also includes financial statements.
  - Letters, reports, and minutes of meetings, 1907-1916, and outlines of books, 1905-1930 (Box 9)
  - Letters and papers, ca. 1906-1928, concerning the publication of books by the Carnegie Institution and the Board of Research Associates (Box 10–11)
  - Letters, reports, and syllabi of books written for the Board of Research Associates, ca. 1906-1927 (Box 11–12)
  - Letters & papers, ca. 1906-1916, including letters from Prof. Farnam & Pres. Butterfield, financial statements, reports, and outlines concerning surveys financed by the Carnegie Institution. (Box 12–13)
  - Annual reports, financial reports, departmental reports, and outlines and bills, 1912-1916, of the Carnegie Institution, department of economics and sociology. (Box 13)
  - Financial reports, checks, bank statements, and papers, 1917-1933, of the Board of Research Associates, including letters and papers, 1916, relative to the separation from Carnegie Institution of Washington. (Box 14)
  - Letters and papers, ca. 1928-1933, concerning books published by the Board of Research Associates: History of Southern Agriculture before 1860 (Box 15)
  - Letters and papers ca. 1911-1917 concerning the publication of books and monographs on agriculture (Box 16)
  - Essay on homestead exemptions, 1910, by Prof. Farnam, and letters by and to Miss. Vera A. Timm ca. 1936-1940 concerning papers of Prof. Farnam.
    General note
    The monographs in this collection, consisting of 31 studies under the direction of Prof, Henry W. Farnam, are catalogued individually under authors. List of authors follows.
  - Monographs
    - Austin, Charles Burgess: Labor Legislation in Indiana, 1908 251 l. typewritten. 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Badger, Ralph Eastman: Report Giving Receipts and Expenditures Connected with the Public Lands Service of the United States, 1888-1913 (1916). 9l. typewritten. 1 folder (Box 17)
    - Baldwin, Foy Spencer, 1870-: Recent Massachusetts Labor Legislation, 1901-1908 (1908). typed. 1 folder (Box 17)
    - Bancroft, Everett Clair: Notes on Laws Regarding Seamen, Immigration, Paupers, etc., 1916. (Box 17)
      California, 2 bundles; Connecticut, 2 bundles; Delaware, 1 bundle; Florida, 1 bundle; Ga., 1 bundle; Maine, 1 bundle; Massachusetts, 2 bundles; Maryland, 1 bundle; New Hampshire, 1 bundle; New Jersey, 1 bundle; New York, 2 bundles; North Carolina, l bundle; Rhode Island, 1 bundle; South Carolina 1 bundle; Virginia, 1 bundle; Chinese and U.S., 1 bundle; U.S. Congressional Laws. Immigration, 1798-1913, 1 bundle. 21 bundles. 2 folders.
    - Barnes, Charles Brinton, 1870-: The Longshoremen, (New York, 1915). Corrected proof sheets of a study published by the Russell Sage foundation. (Box 18)
    - Bedford, Scott Elias William, 1876-: The Labor Legislation of Kansas, 1909. 330l. typewritten 3 folders. Filed with this are three letters to Bedford from: Frank Gilday, 1911 Mar 31; Thomas Morrissey, 1911 Jun 13 and Leon Besson, 1911 Sep 27 (Box 18)
    - Coulter, John Lee, 1881-: The Public Land Policy of Dakota Territory and North and South Dakota, 1909. 145l. typewritten. 1 folder. Completed 1909 Jun 10. (Box 18)
    - Crafer, Thomas Woodside Bentley
      - The Administration of Public Poor Relief in Wisconsin. Part I of a monograph for the Carnegie institution of Wash. D.C. 1907. 106l. typewritten. 1 folder; Part II of a monograph for the Carnegie Institution of Wash. D.C. 1907. 112l. typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 18)
      - Trade Unions and the Law in Wisconsin, 1909.160l. typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 18)
    - Diamond, Herbert Maynard, 1892-: Federal Children's Bureau, 1915. 14l. typewritten. 1 folder (Box 18)
    - Downey, Ezekiel Henry, 1879-1922: History of Labor Legislation on Iowa, 1910. Published, Iowa Economic History Series, State Historical Society of Iowa. Edited by Benjamin F. Shambaugh, Iowa City, 1910. 394l. typewritten. 2 folders. (Box 19)
    - Dozier, Howard Douglass: A Brief History of the Public School System of Tennessee, 1916. 20l typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 19)
    - Edward, Alba M, 1872-1947: Federal Legislation for the Protection of American Seamen. New Haven, Conn., 1907. 2 bundles of notes. The Legislation of the New England States Governing the Descent and Distribution of Property. 1907. 292l manuscript. 1 folder. The Maritime Hospital Service of the United States. New Haven, 1907.114l+ tp. and table of contents. 1 notebook. (Box 19)
    - Field, Arthur Sargent, 1874-1932: The Child Labor and Factory Law of New Jersey (A thesis submitted to the faculty of social science in Yale University for part of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy, 1909 May 1) Published American Economic Association, 3d series, xi, no. 3, Cambridge, Mass. pp.229, 1910 under title, "The Child Labor Policy of New Jersey." 313l. typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 20)
    - Hagerty, James Edward: The History of the Poor Laws of Ohio, Indiana, & Illinois, 1908 by James E. Hagerty and Beatrice H. Sheets. 301l. typewritten. 2 volumes. (Box 20)
    - Isaacs, Nathan: The Mining Laws of Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois, 1908 (Box 20)
    - McKitrick, Reuben: Syllabus of a Report to Carnegie Institution on the Legislative Disposition of Public Lands in Texas, 1908. 44l. typed. 1 folder. The Public Land System of Texas, 1911, published as "The public land system of Texas, 1823-1910", in bull. of the Univ. of Wisconsin, no. 905, economics and political science series, IX no. 1, pp. 1-172, Madison, Wis., 1918. Also reprinted in part in Farnam, Henry W., Chapters in the history of social legislation in the United States to 1860, Washington, D.C. 1938, pp.140-147. 1971 typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 20)
    - Parry, Carl E.: Labor Legislation of Michigan, 1909 303l. typewritten. 2 folders. (Box 21)
    - Peacock, D.L.
      - Interviews with Southern men. Collected for social legislation of the southern states: Administration officials, bank officers, lawyers, and judges, men connected with educational institutions, colored people, cotton dealers, and merchants, plantation owners and superintendents, miscellaneous interviews. Material collected in 1906 & 1907. 127l typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 21)
      - Laws of the Reconstruction Period Relating to Labor, circa 1910. 117l. typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 21)
      - Mining Legislation in the Southern States, 1909. 263l. MS. 1 folder (Box 21)
    - Riley, Thomas James, 1870-: A History of the Poor Law and of Poor Relief in Missouri, Being an Account of the Legislative and Institutional Development of the State's Charities, 1909. 70l. typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 21)
    - Sheets, Beatrice H: A History of the Poor Laws of Ohio, 1909 by James E. Hagerty and Beatrice H. Sheets. 110l. typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 21)
    - Steele, H. Wirt: Labor Legislation in Maryland ,1908. 211l. typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 21)
    - Towles, John Ker, 1880-: Factory Legislation in Rhode Island, 1908 155l. typewritten. 1 volume. (Box 22)
    - Underwood, J. Harding: Homesteads and Exemptions, 1909. 170l. typewritten. 1 folder. (Box 22)
  - Carnegie Institution of Washington Department of Economics and Sociology Account book, 1907-1908 (Filed alone at end of collection), 1907-1933 (Box 23)
    Laid in is Examination of accounts, 1917-1933 by Petze and Schuyler.